Guide to the Leonidas Westerwelt Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Leonidas Westerwelt Papers,
1816-1950
Westervelt, Leonidas, 1875-1952.
4.5 linear ft. (141 items in 8 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
4079459
Biographical Note
American playwright, collector of theatrical books and manuscripts.
Scope and Content
Correspondence and manuscripts of Westervelt. Much of the correspondence relates to the production of his own plays. Also, letters from famous actors including William Charles Macready, Augustin Daly, and Charles Kemble; typescript manuscripts of Westervelt's plays, among them "By Right of Sword" and "Rally Round the Flag;" and contracts, photographs, and printed materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Books
Series III: Printed Materials
Series IV: Books by G. Kunz
Series V: Contracts and Photographs
Series VI: Manuscripts of Plays
Subjects
Macready, William, d. 1829.; Daly, Augustin, 1838-1899.; Kemble, Charles, 1775-1854.; Actors.; Drama.; Theater--Production and direction.; Theater.; Scripts.; Photoprints.; Autographs.; Dramatists, American.; Book collectors.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-9. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1960 M-60 Westervelt, Mrs. Leonidas Gift
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Adams, Maud To Mrs. Doremus New York, [n.d.], (1 page a.l.s) (Box 1)
  - Allen, Viola To Mrs. Doremus [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Anthony, Luther B. To Leonidas Westervelt Easton, PA, 1 February 1913, (1 page t.l.s) (Box 1)
  - Arliss, George To Leonidas Westervelt London & New York, 24 September 1923 & 22 November 1937, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Aronson, Rudolph To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 31 January & 20 April 1918, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Babbage, Charles To William Charles Macready London, 3 October 1837, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    (Written in the third person)
  - Barrie, James M. To Leonidas Westervelt London, 30 October 1897, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Bolton, Reginald Pelham To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 1924-1939, (3 a.l.s. 3 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Breton, Cecil To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 6 December [1904], (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Calver, William Louis To Leonidas Westervelt [v.p.], 1930-1939, (9 a.l.s. 3 p.c.s.) (Box 1)
  - Chaillu, P.B. Du To [Leonidas Westervelt] Carmel, 9 July 1855, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Cheatham, Kitty To [Leonidas Westervelt] New York, 12 November [n.y.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Clark, James L. To Leonidas Westervelt [n.p.], 7 November 1930, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Daly, Augustin Photograph inscribed to J. W. Bouton New York, 6 March 1871, (1 photograph) (Box 1)
  - Daly, Augustin To Mr. Deacon New York, 15 January 1891, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Daly, Augustin To Douglas Taylor New York, 31 October 1896, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - de Wolfe, Elsie To Mrs. Leonidas Westervelt New York, [n.d.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Dobson, Austin To A. C. Benson London, 28 December 1896, (1 page a.l.s) (Box 1)
    (with envelope)
  - Doremus, Bessie W. To Leonidas Westervelt [n.p.] & New York, [n.d.] & 1934, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Edeson, Robert To Leonidas Westervelt Kansas City, 3 January 1911, (1 page a.l.s) (Box 1)
    (With attached photograph)
  - Elliott, Maxine To Mrs. Doremus New York, 5 January 1909, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Farquhar, Gilbert To Mrs. Leonidas Westervelt New York, 14 December 1904, (3 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Fawcett, Edgar To Mr. Mallory New York, [n.d.], (3 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Fawcett, John To Mr. Mathews [London], 1 January 1824, (1 page a.l.s) (Box 1)
    (Gift of Mary S. Rouse, 1965)
  - Foote, Maria To Mr. Aubyn London, 20 June 1816, (1 page a.l.s) (Box 1)
  - Frohman, Charles To Charles Burnham New York, 8 January 1910 & 25 June 1915, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Frohman, Charles To Mr. Milliken New York, 23 February 1917, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Frohman, Daniel To Mrs. Charles A. Doremus New York, 24 December 1898, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Geary, Mary To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 9 September 1904, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Gillett, William To Mr. Ries [n.p.], [1890], (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Gillett, William To Mr. Mallory Boston, 27 February 1918, (3 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Hackett, James K. To Leonidas Westervelt [n.p.], 4 July 1899, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Harvey, Edward Tutin To William Winter Cincinnati, 20 December 1915, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
    (With envelope)
  - Hodge, William To Mrs. Charles A. Doremus Cohasset, [n.d.], (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Kemble, Charles To [?] London, 13 March 1819, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - La Follette, Fola To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 6 November 1911, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Larrimore, Francine To Leonidas Westervelt [New York], [ca. 1917], (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Liston, John To [?] London, 2 February 1828, (1 page a.l.s) (Box 1)
  - Littlebury, Joseph To Leonidas Westervelt Worcester, England, 4 October 1922, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Lytton, Edward Robert Bulwer To Lord Malmesbury [n.p.], 21 July [n.y.], (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Macready, William Charles To [?] [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Macready, William Charles To Mr. Fenton New York, 20 September [n.y.], (3 page a.l.s) (Box 1)
  - Mapes, Victor To Leonidas Westervelt [v.p.], 30 October [n.y.] - 12 May 1898, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Marchmont, Arthur W. To Mr. & Mrs. Leonidas Westervelt [v.p.], 4 June 1899 - 12 July 1898, (6 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Matthews, Brander To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 19 January 1904, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Middleton, George To Leonidas Westervelt Atlantic City, 24 November 1913, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Mordant, Edwin To Leonidas Westervelt New York & Hollywood, 3 April 1927 - 16 May 1933 1, (a.l.s. 3 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Mordant, Grace (Mrs. Edwin) To Leonidas Westervelt Detroit, 14 October 1930, (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Morris, Felix To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 20 March 1897 - 13 November 1899, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Marchmont, Arthur W. To Leonidas Westervelt London, 31 October 1898 & 16 June 1899, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Maude, Cyril To Leonidas Westervelt London, 11 December 1912, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Mellen, Ida M. To Leonidas Westervelt New York & Woods Hole, MA, 1925-1943, (5 t.l.s. 6 p.c.s. 1 photograph) (Box 1)
  - Odell, George Clinton Dinsmore To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 7 December 1945, (2 page a.l.s. ) (Box 1)
    (Removed from Odell Annals of the New York Stage, vol 14)
  - Orsay, Count Alfred Guillaume Gabriel d' To Leonidas Westervelt [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 page a.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Rawson, Clayton To Leonidas Westervelt Mamaroneck, NY, [n.d.] & 1 April 1940, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Sage, C. Russell To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 14 March 1905 4 page a.l.s. 1 Smith, Albert To [?] London, [n.d.], (2 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Spong, Hilda To Mrs. Doremus New York, 18 February 1917, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Stuart, Ralph To Leonidas Westervelt [v.p.], 6 December 1901 - 9 October 1902, (1 a.l.s. 4 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Talfourd, Thomas Noon To Miss Jones [n.p.], 1836, (1 page a.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Vokes, Rosina (Mrs. Cecil Clay) To [?] Chicago, 5 January [n.y.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Wagenencht, Edward To Leonidas Westervelt WA & IL, 25 January 1930 - 25 December 1949, (6 t.l.s. 1 p.c.s.) (Box 1)
  - Walker, Charlotte To Leonidas Westervelt [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Walsh, Townsend To Leonidas Westervelt New York, 21-27 January 1928, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Wilson, Francis To Leonidas Westervelt Philadelphia, [25 December] 1890, (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Young, Charles Mayne To Lady Catherine [n.p.], 7 June 1847, (1 page a.l.s) (Box 1)
  - Zabriskie, George A. To Leonidas Westervelt NY & FL, 29 April 1942 - 19 July 1950, (9 a.l.s. 1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
- Series II: Books
  - Books (Box 2-3)
- Series III: Printed Materials
  - Printed Materials (Box 4-8)
- Series IV: Books by G. Kunz
  - Inscribed to Westervelt (Box 5-6)
- Series V: Contracts and Photographs
  - Contracts and Photographs (Box 7)
- Series VI: Manuscripts of Plays
  - Manuscripts of Plays (Box 9)